

#### Department of Computer Science, ETH Zurich □+41 764999105 | Si.liu@inf.ethz.ch

#### Research Interests

Si Liu's research interests are broadly in formal methods, software engineering, distributed systems, cybersecurity, and the intersection of them. His current work focuses on verifying & validating the designs & deployments of databases, the DNS, and AI systems, addressing both qualitative (e.g., reliability and robustness) & quantitative (e.g., availability and scalability) aspects.

#### Education

# University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign (UIUC)

PHD IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Aug. 2012 - May 2019

• Advisor: Prof. Dr. Jose Meseguer

## East China Normal University (ECNU)

MASTER IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Sep. 2009 - May 2012

• Advisor: Prof. Dr. Huibiao Zhu

## East China Normal University (ECNU)

**BACHELOR IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING** Sep. 2005 - Jun. 2009

# Professional Experience \_\_\_\_

May 2023 – Present	Senior Researcher (Deutsch: Oberassistent), ETH Zurich
Aug. 2019 – May 2023	Postdoc Researcher, ETH Zurich

Sep. 2014 – Sep. 2017 Research Assistant, Assured Cloud Computing Center, UIUC Jun. 2011 – Aug. 2011 Research Intern, National Cyber-Physical Systems Camp, USTC Sep. 2009 – May 2012 Research Assistant, Danish-Chinese Research Center, ECNU

May 2008 – Feb. 2009 Software Engineering Intern, Dept. of Talent House, Hewlett-Packard Co. Ltd.

#### Publications \_\_\_\_\_

#### **UNDER SUBMISSION**

- [VLDB'25] Shabnam Ghasemirad<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu, Luca Multazzu, Christoph Sprenger, David Basin. Verlso: Verifiable Isolation Guarantees for Database Transactions
  - [-'25] Dhruv Nevatia<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu, David Basin. Reachability Analysis of the Domain Name System
  - [-'25] Jiang Xiao<sup>†</sup>, **Si Liu**, Hengfeng Wei. Boosting Database Isolation Checking via Mini-Transactions
  - [-'25] Zhiheng Cai, Si Liu\*, Hengfeng Wei. Uniso: A Unified Framework for Efficiently Checking Database Isolation Guarantees.
  - [-'25] Shi Peng<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu, Peixin Wang, Chenyang Xu, Cheng Chen, Dapeng Zhi, Min Zhang. ATA: An Abstract-Train-Abstract Approach for Explanation-Friendly Deep Reinforcement Learning

#### **PUBLISHED**

- [OOPSLA'24] Si Liu, Long Gu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. Plume: Efficient and Complete Black-box Checking of Weak Isolation Levels
- [SIGMOD'24] Si Liu, Luca Multazzu, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin. NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Distributed Transactions

<sup>\*</sup> I contributed equally as a co-first author † indicates the students I supervised

- [VLDB'24] Long Gu<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu, Tiancheng Xing, Hengfeng Wei, Yuxing Chen, David Basin. IsoVista: Black-box Checking Database Isolation Guarantees. *Demonstration track*.
- [USENIX SEC'24] Huayi Duan, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, David Basin, Si Liu, Bernhard Tellenbach. CAMP: Compositional Amplification Attacks against DNS
  - [CAV'24] Dapeng Zhi, Peixin Wang, Si Liu, Luke Ong and Min Zhang. Unifying Qualitative and Quantitative Safety Verification of DNN-Controlled Systems
  - [VMCAl'24] Jiaxu Tian<sup>†</sup>, Dapeng Zhi, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Guy Katz, Min Zhang. Taming Reachability Analysis of DNN-Controlled Systems via Abstraction-Based Training
  - [SIGCOMM'23] Si Liu, Huayi Duan, Lukas Heimes, Marco Bearzi, Jodok Vieli, Adrian Perrig, and David Basin. A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution
    - [VLDB'23] Kaile Huang, Si Liu\*, Zhenge Chen, Hengfeng Wei, David Basin, Haixiang Li, and Anqun Pan. Efficient Black-box Checking of Snapshot Isolation in Databases
    - [OSDI'23] Zu-Ming Jiang, Si Liu, Manuel Rigger, and Zhendong Su. Detecting Transactional Bugs in Database Engines via Graph-Based Oracle Construction
    - [NeurIPS'23] Jiaxu Tian<sup>†</sup>, Dapeng Zhi, **Si Liu**, Peixin Wang, Cheng Chen, and Min Zhang. Boosting Verification of Deep Reinforcement Learning via Piece-Wise Linear Decision Neural Networks
      - [NSDI'23] Huayi Duan, Fischer Ruben, Lou Jie, Si Liu, David Basin, and Adrian Perrig. RHINE: Robust and High-performance Internet Naming with E2E Authenticity
      - [ISSTA'23] Zhiyi Xue<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu, Zhaodi Zhang, Yiting Wu, and Min Zhang. A Tale of Two Approximations: Tight-ening Over-Approximation for DNN Robustness Verification via Under-Approximation
      - [CVPR'23] Zhaodi Zhang<sup>†</sup>, Zhiyi Xue<sup>†</sup>, Yang Chen, **Si Liu**, Yueling Zhang, Jing Liu, and Min Zhang. Boosting Verified Training for Robust Image Classifications via Abstraction
    - [OOPSLA'22] Si Liu, Jose Meseguer, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, David Basin. Bridging the Semantic Gap between Qualitative and Quantitative Models of Distributed Systems
    - [TOSEM'22] Si Liu. All in One: Design, Verification, and Implementation of SNOW-Optimal Read Atomic Transactions
      - [CSF'22] Thilo Weghorn, Si Liu\*, Christoph Sprenger, Adrian Perrig, David Basin. N-Tube: Formally Verified Secure Bandwidth Reservation in Path-Aware Internet Architectures
      - [ASE'22] Zhaodi Zhang<sup>†</sup>, Yiting Wu, **Si Liu**, Jing Liu, Min Zhang. Provably Tightest Linear Approximation for Robustness Verification of Sigmoid-like Neural Networks
      - [TASE'21] Lei Liang<sup>†</sup>, Si Liu. Exploring Design Alternatives for Replicated RAMP Transactions Using Maude
      - [NFM'20] Si Liu, Atul Sandur, Jose Meseguer, Peter Olveczky, Qi Wang. Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs
    - **[TACAS'19] Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Olveczky, Min Zhang, Qi Wang, Jose Meseguer. Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude.
      - [CCS'19] Qi Wang, Pubali Datta, Wei Yang, Si Liu, Carl Gunter, Adam Bates. Charting the Attack Surface of Trigger-Action IoT Platforms.
      - **[FAoC'19] Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Read Atomic Transactions with Prevention of Lost Updates: ROLA and Its Formal Analysis. *Formal Aspects of Computing*
      - [FASE'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Keshav Santhanam, Qi Wang, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. ROLA: A New Distributed Transaction Protocol and Its Formal Analysis.
    - [LITES'17] Si Liu, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Son Nguyen, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer.

      Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Leibniz Transactions on Embedded Systems*
    - [ICFEM'17] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking.
    - [**JLAMP'16**] **Si Liu**, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, José Meseguer. Modeling and Analyzing Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. *Journal of Logical and Algebraic Methods in Programming* 
      - [SAC'16] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Jatin Ganhotra, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems.

- [**QEST'15**] **Si Liu**, Son Nguyen, Jatin Ganhotra, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. *Nominated for Best Paper.*
- [ICFEM'14] Si Liu, Muntasir Raihan Rahman, Stephen Skeirik, Indranil Gupta, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude.
- [PRDC'14] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu and Yongxin Zhao. Reasoning about Group-Based Mobility in MANETs.
- [ComSIS'13] Xi Wu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Zheng Wang, Si Liu. Modeling and verifying the Ariadne protocol using process algebra. *Computer Science and Information Systems Journal* 
  - [ECBS'12] Xi Wu, Si Liu, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, Lei Chen. Modeling and Verifying the Ariadne Protocol Using CSP.
  - [HASE'11] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective.
  - [TASE'11a] Si Liu, Yongxin Zhao, Huibiao Zhu, Qin Li. Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks.
  - **[TASE'11b]** Mengying Wang, Huibiao Zhu, Yongxin Zhao, **Si Liu**. Modeling and Analyzing the  $\mu$ TESLA Protocol Using CSP.
- [ICECCS'11] Yongxin Zhao, Yanhong Huang, Jifeng He, Si Liu. Formal Model of Interrupt Program from a Probabilistic Perspective.
  - [SSIRI'11] Si Liu, Xiaofeng Wu, Qin Li, Huibiao Zhu, Qian Wang. Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks.
  - [UTP'10] Qin Li, Yongxin Zhao, Xiaofeng Wu, Si Liu. Promoting Models.

#### WORKSHOP PAPERS

- [WRLA'18] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Qi Wang, José Meseguer. Formal Modeling and Analysis of the Walter Transactional Data Store.
  - [SSS'15] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. Formal analysis of Leader Election in MANETs Using Real-Time Maude.
- [WRLA'14] Si Liu, Peter Csaba Ölveczky and José Meseguer. A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude.
- [SSIRI'11] Han Zhu, Huibiao Zhu, Si Liu, Jian Guo. Towards Denotational Semantics for Verilog in PVS.

#### **BOOK CHAPTERS**

- David Basin, Tobias Klenze, **Si Liu**, Christoph Sprenger. *Design-Level Verification* in *The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification*. 2022.
- Giacomo Giuliari, Markus Legner, **Si Liu**, Adrian Perrig, Thilo Weghorn, Marc Wyss. *Extensions for the Data Plane* in *The Complete Guide to SCION: From Design Principles to Formal Verification*. 2022.
- Rakesh Bobba, Jon Grov, Indranil Gupta, **Si Liu**, José Meseguer, Peter Csaba Ölveczky, Stephen Skeirik. Survivability: Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. 2018.

#### **PHD THESIS**

• Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign. 2019

# Teaching Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Fall 2024	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2024	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2023	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2023	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2022	<b>Information Systems for Engineers</b> , Head Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich

Spring 2022	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2021	Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2021	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2020	Computer Systems, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Spring 2020	Data Modeling and Databases, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2019	Applied Security Lab, Teaching Assistant	ETH Zurich
Fall 2016	<b>Distributed Systems</b> , Teaching Assistant	UIUC
Fall 2011	Process Algebra, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Spring 2011	Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Fall 2010	Discrete Mathematics, Teaching Assistant	ECNU
Spring 2010	Algorithms and Data Structures, Teaching Assistant	ECNU

# Mentoring\_

#### PhD students

- Dhruv Nevatia (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (co-supervised with Dr. Christoph Sprenger and Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Zijing Yin (co-supervised with Prof. David Basin), ETH Zurich
- Ziwei Zhou (co-supervised with Dr. Hengfeng Wei and Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Shi Peng(co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang), ECNU
- Zhaodi Zhang (co-supervised with Prof. Min Zhang; first employment: Chengdu Education Research Institute), ECNU

### Graduate students

- Theodor Moroianu, ETH Zurich
- Yunxin Sun, ETH Zurich
- Yufei Zhang, ETH Zurich
- Rolando Grave de Peralta, ETH Zurich
- Zhou Zhou, ECNU
- Long Gu, Nanjing University
- Qiuhuan Xiong, Nanjing University
- Luca Multazz (first employment: SICPA), ETH Zurich
  - \* honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "NOCS-Optimal Distributed Transactions and Beyon" (top 2.5%)
- Lukas Heimes (first employment: SBB CFF FFS), ETH Zurich
  - \* honoured with the ETH Medal for his Master thesis "A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution" (top 2.5%)
- Jodok Vieli (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Marco Bearzi (graduated), ETH Zurich
- Shabnam Ghasemirad (now PhD at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich
- Jiang Xiao (first employment: Agricultural Bank of China), Nanjing University

- Jiaxu Tian (first employment: CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Zhiyi Xue (now PhD at ECNU), ECNU

### Undergraduate students

- Tiancheng Xing (graduated, now Master at NUS), Nanjing University
- Zhiheng Cai (graduated, now PhD at Tsinghua University), Nanjing University
- Long Gu (graduated, now Master at Nanjing University), Nanjing University
- Zhenge Chen (graduated, now Master at UCSD), Nanjing University
- Teng Wang (graduated), Nanjing University
- Zhou Zhou (graduated, now Master at ECNU), ECNU
- Ziwei Zhou (graduated, now PhD at ECNU), ECNU
- Ruiyang Liu (graduated, now Master at JHU), ECNU
- Lei Liang (graduated, now at CITIC Securities), ECNU
- Plamen Stefanov (graduated, now Master at ETH Zurich), ETH Zurich
- Keshav Santhanam (graduated, now PhD at Stanford University), UIUC

## Professional Activities \_\_\_\_

- Program Committee Member: NSDI'25, ICFEM'24, ICFEM'23
- Journal Reviewer: JLAMP
- **Sub-Reviewer:** ICFEM'22, FM'21, FM'18, ICFEM'16, FASE'14, ICFEM'14, ICFEM'13, ICFEM'12, TASE'12, ICFEM'11, TASE'11, ICFEM'10
- Dagstuhl Seminar: "Ensuring the Reliability and Robustness of Database Management Systems (21442)"
   2021
- **Grant Proposal:** preparing proposal for NSF CNS 1409416 (\$584,000, 2014 2017), Availability-Consistency Tradeoffs in Key-Value and NoSQL Storage Systems

#### Awards & Honors \_\_\_\_\_

2024 Career Seed Award, ETH Zurich

CHF 30,000

- The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis "NOCS-Optimal Distributed Transactions and Beyond" (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich
- The ETH Medal for supervised Master thesis "A Formal Framework for End-to-End DNS Resolution" (Top 2.5%), ETH Zurich
- 2012 Outstanding Graduate Award, East China Normal University
- 2011 Excellent Student Award (Ranked 1st), East China Normal University

#### Talks & Presentations

• NOC-NOC: Towards Performance-optimal Dis-tributed Transactions. SIGMOD'24, Santiago, Chile, 2024.

- Generating Correct-by-Construction Distributed Implementations from Formal Maude Designs. NFM'20, Virtual, 2020.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. University Paris Diderot, France, 2019.
- Design, Verification and Automatic Implementation of Correct-by-Construction Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. ETH Zurich, Switzerland, 2019.
- Automatic Analysis of Consistency Properties of Distributed Transaction Systems in Maude. TACAS'19, Prague, Czech Republic, 2019.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for RAMP Transactions through Statistical Model Checking. ICFEM'17, Xi'an, China, 2017.
- Design, Formal Modeling, and Validation of Cloud Storage Systems using Maude. Huawei, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Exploring Design Alternatives for the RAMP Transaction System Through Statistical Model Checking. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2017.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. SAC'16, Pisa, Italy, 2016.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Ramp Transaction Systems. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2016.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. QEST'15, Madrid, Spain, 2015.
- Quantitative Analysis of Consistency in NoSQL Key-value Stores. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2015.
- A Framework for Mobile Ad hoc Networks in Real-Time Maude. WRLA'14, Grenoble, France, 2014.
- Formal Modeling and Analysis of Cassandra in Maude. Assured Cloud Computing Center, Urbana-Champaign, USA, 2014.
- A Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks from a Group Probabilistic Perspective. HASE'11, Boca Raton, USA, 2011.
- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. University of Science and Technology of China, Suzhou, China, 2011.
- Towards a Probabilistic Calculus for Mobile Ad Hoc Networks. TASE'11, Xi'an, China, 2011.
- Formal Approaches to Wireless Sensor Networks. SSIRI'11, Jeju Island, Korea, 2011.